Translator's note
Now we were talking about the necessity
of human beings changing,
and why they don't change,
why they accept these
intolerable conditions of human psyche.
I think we ought to go
or approach the same thing from a different angle.
Who has invented this unconscious?
Who has invented it?
I think the unconscious,
there's a difference between what we call the unconscious
and what is the unconscious.
The word is not the thing.
Yes, the word is not the thing.
Who has thought it up?
Well, I think the history
of the thinking about the unconscious
is a long and involved process.
I think it began
in the early 20th century.
May we ask, have you an unconscious?
Again, we're into a language problem.
Have I an unconscious?
Are you aware of your unconscious?
Do you know you have an unconscious
that is operating differently
or trying to give you hints?
You know, all that.
Are you aware of all that?
Yes.
I am aware,
of an aspect of myself
that I look at it a little differently.
I look at it that there's an aspect of myself
that is aware incompletely.
That's what I call the unconscious.
It is aware of my experience
or aware of the events
in an incomplete way.
That's what I call the unconscious.
Now, it uses symbols
and different modes of telling me,
of understanding.
In other words, a dream
where I am discovering jealousy
in the dream, right?
That I wasn't aware of.
But would you also give importance
or were you, Dr. Bohm,
a feeling that there is such a thing?
Well, I don't know what we mean by that.
I think we can...
The phenomena are that there are some things we do
whose origin we're not aware of.
You see, we react,
we use words in a habitual way.
We have dreams.
I mean, I suppose we...
I'm going to question all that,
because I am not sure...
You're questioning that we have dreams.
No.
But I want to question or ask the experts
if there is such a thing as the unconscious.
For me, somehow,
I don't think it has played any important part
in my life at all.
Well, it depends on what you mean
by the unconscious.
I'll tell you what I mean.
Something hidden,
something incomplete,
something that I have to go after
consciously or unconsciously.
You know, go after and discover it,
unearth it, explore it and expose it.
Right, right.
See the motives,
see the hidden intentions.
Right, right.
Well, could we make it clear, though,
that there are some things people do
where you can see they are not aware
of what they are doing,
but some things of the nature of thought.
I don't quite follow.
Well, people are...
For example, you know,
this Freudian slip of the tongue,
you know, that somebody makes a slip of the tongue
which expresses his real intention, you see.
Oh, yes, yes, yes.
I didn't mean that, quite.
I mean, in that sense...
That would be an unconscious.
That's what people think of as the unconscious.
You see, I think there are two problems
here, if I can just
put in a technical statement here.
There are those people,
and there has arisen in the history
of thinking about the unconscious,
people who think that there are...
like the unconscious is a thing
and that there are things in the unconscious
which are there and must be lifted out.
Then I think that there's
a large group of people now
who think of the unconscious as areas of behavior
or areas of response
or areas of experience that are not...
all the connections, we aren't aware,
totally aware of all that goes into what happened.
So that in the daytime you might have,
let's say, an experience of stress
or like you would say a disorder.
You didn't finish with the experience.
And at night you go
through reworking in a new way.
You have no other way.
So that would be the unconscious
and you get other, let's say, from the past
or from previous programs of action.
I mean, the collective unconscious,
the racial unconscious.
Let's say somebody has been deeply hurt in the past
and you can see his
whole behavior is governed by that,
though he doesn't know, he may not know it.
Yes, that I understand.
His response is always on the basis of the past.
Quite.
What I'm trying to find out is
why we have divided it,
the conscious and the unconscious.
Or is it one unitary total process, moving,
not hidden, not concealed,
but moving as a whole current.
And we come along,
clever, brainy birds come along
and split it up
and say there is the unconscious and the conscious,
the hidden, the incomplete,
the storehouse of racial memories,
family memories, G, all that.
Well, the reason that happened, I think,
is that, well, just partially explained,
is the fact that Freud and Jung
and these people that were seeing patients,
out of which grew so much of the knowledge
about the unconscious,
would see patients, people who had separated it,
in other words, had fragmented off this movement
that you're talking about.
That's what I want to get at.
Right.
In other words, a woman who says that she is...
the whole history of hysteria,
you know, where patients couldn't move their arm.
I know.
You know about that.
And then if you open up the memory,
Yes.
for a certain reason,
then they eventually can move the arm.
So they put two and two together.
They don't think it worked that way,
but that's the way they did it.
Or there were people who had dual personalities.
What I'm trying to...
Is it an insanity?
Not insanity.
Is it a state of mind that divides everything
that says there is the unconscious, conscious?
It is a process of fragmentation also.
Right.
Well, wouldn't you say that certain material
is made...
Even Freud has said that certain material
is made unconscious by the brain
because it's too disturbing.
That's what I was...
It's fragmented.
I mean, that's well known in all forms of psychology.
That's right.
That's what I'm saying.
That it's fragmented off,
and that then was called the unconscious.
What is fragmented is the unconscious.
I understand that.
But that meant...
Would one say that the brain itself is purposely,
or in some sense, holding it separate,
to avoid it, you see?
Yes, avoid facing the facts.
That's right.
Yes, so that it's not really separate from consciousness.
That's what I want to get at, you see?
Yes.
It is...
Right.
I mean, it isn't separate from consciousness.
The brain has organised in a fragmented way.
Yes, but then it's the wrong terminology to call it...
You see, the word unconscious already implies separation.
Separation.
So say there are two layers, for example,
the deep unconscious and the surface conscious.
Right, right.
That structure is implied.
That's right.
But now this other notion is to say there's no...
that structure is not implied, but rather certain material,
wherever it may be, is simply avoided.
That's right.
That's the way I think about it.
I don't want to think
about somebody because he's hurting me.
Right.
That's not the...
It's I don't want to think about it.
That's right.
I'm conscious, he's hurt me, and
I don't want to think about it.
But there's kind of a paradoxical...
situation arises because eventually you
become so good at it...
that you don't realise you're doing it.
I mean, that seems to happen, you see.
Yes, yes, yes.
That people become so proficient at avoiding these things...
that they cease to realise they're doing it.
That's right.
Yes.
It becomes habitual.
That's right.
I mean, I think this is
what happens, that these kinds of things...
That is, the wound remains.
The wound remains and we forget that we've forgotten.
The wound remains.
Right.
I suppose we remember to forget this.
Yes.
We remember to forget.
And the process, actually the process of therapy...
is helping the remembering, you see, and the recall.
To remember you've forgotten...
and then to understand the connections of why you forgot...
and then the thing can
move in a more holistic way...
rather than being fragmented.
Do you consider...
or feel that you've been hurt?
Yes.
And want to avoid it?
Or being hurt, resist, withdraw, isolate...
the whole picture, the image
of yourself being hurt and withdrawn...
all that.
Do you feel that when you are hurt?
Yes.
I feel...
How to put it?
I think it's too...
I'm interested in this.
Let's go into this.
Yes, I feel there is definitely
a move not to be hurt...
not to be...
not to have that image...
not to have that whole thing changed.
Because if it's changed...
it seems to catapult into that
same experience that was the hurt.
See, it may not...
this is hurt...
but this has a resonation with that unconscious...
which reminds me...
you see, I am reminded of being hurt deeply...
by this more superficial hurt.
I understand that.
So that I avoid hurt, period.
Can the brain have a shock?
Of course, all the rest of biological, physical shock.
But this psychological brain, if I can call it...
Right.
Must it be hurt?
Is that inevitable?
No, I don't think so.
It's only hurt with reference to something.
No, I'm asking...
can such a...
psychological brain, if I can use those two words...
never be hurt?
Under any circumstances, given...
you know...
family life, husband, wife...
bad friends, so-called enemies...
all that's going on around you...
and never get hurt.
Because apparently...
this is one of the major wounds...
in human existence...
to get hurt.
The more sensitive you are...
the more aware...
you get more and more hurt...
more and more withdrawn.
Is this inevitable?
You're asking...
I don't think it's inevitable...
but I think it happens...
frequently, I mean more often than not.
And it happens...
when...
it seems to happen...
when there is...
how can I describe it...
an attachment is formed...
and then the loss of the attachment.
You become important to me.
What you think...
you become important to me...
I like you or I get involved with you.
Then it becomes important to me...
that you don't do anything...
that disturbs that image.
That is, in that relationship...
between two people...
the picture that we have...
of each other...
the image of...
that is the cause of hurt.
But it also goes the other way...
that we hold those images...
because of hurt.
Of course, of course.
Where does it start?
That's what I want to get at.
Yes, I mean...
that's what I want to get at too.
No, you pointed out something.
Right.
I know he did, yes.
Because the hurt...
the past hurt...
gives a tremendous strength...
to the image.
To the image.
The image which helps us...
to forget it, right?
That's right.
Now, is this wound...
in the unconscious...
we'll use the word unconscious...
in quotes for the time being...
is that hidden?
Well, let's...
I think you are being a little simplistic...
about that because...
what is hidden...
is the fact that...
I've had the event happen many times.
It happened with my mother...
it happened with my friends...
it's happened before...
School...
There's school...
where I cared about somebody...
and then the image...
I mean, it's like you form the attachment...
and then the hurt.
I'm not at all sure...
through attachment it comes.
I think it's something...
maybe it's not attachment...
maybe that's the wrong word...
but there's something there...
that happens.
What happens...
that I form a relationship with you...
where an image becomes important?
What you do to me becomes important?
You have an image about yourself.
That's right.
And you're saying that I like you...
because you're confirming my image?
No, no, no.
Apart from like and dislike...
apart from like and dislike...
you have an image about yourself.
Right.
I come along...
put a pin in that image.
No, first you come along...
and confirm it.
No.
The hurt will be greater...
if you first come along...
and be very friendly to me...
and confirm the image...
and then suddenly put the pin in.
Of course, of course.
That's right.
That's of course.
But even somebody...
who didn't confirm it...
if he puts the pin in properly...
he can produce that hurt, right?
That's right.
That's not unconscious.
But how come, like you said...
why did I have the image to begin with?
That is unconscious.
Is it unconscious?
That's what I want to get at.
Or it is so obvious...
that we refuse...
that we don't look.
You follow what I'm saying?
I follow what you say, yes.
I'm with you on this and...
We put it away.
We say it's hidden.
I question it...
whether it's hidden at all.
It's so blatantly obvious.
I wonder if all the ingredients of it...
I tell you...
I don't feel all parts of it are obvious.
I think that we hide it in one sense.
Say we say that this hurt means...
that everything is wrong with the image...
but we hide it by saying...
everything is all right, you see, for example.
In other words, the thing that is obvious...
may be hidden by saying it's unimportant...
or that we don't notice it.
Yes, we don't notice it.
But it's like I get the feeling...
as we're talking personally...
I get the feeling there's a kind of...
I ask myself what is it...
that kind of generates the image?
What is that hurt?
We'll come to that.
I mean, I'm trying...
and we're enquiring on...
into the whole structure of consciousness.
Right, right.
That's just what we're enquiring on.
That's what I was coming here.
Into the nature of consciousness.
We have broken it up...
into the hidden and open.
It may be...
the fragmented mind is doing that.
That's right.
And therefore strengthening both.
Dividing...
the division grows greater and greater and greater.
The fragmented mind...
is doing this.
Now, most people have an image about themselves...
practically everybody.
Right.
Practically everybody.
It is that image that gets hurt.
And that image is you.
And you say, well, I am hurt.
That's the same as we were discussing this morning.
Yes.
You see, if I say I have a pleasant self-image...
then I attribute the pleasure to me.
Right?
And saying that's real.
And then if somebody hurts me...
then the pain is attributed to me.
And I say that's real too.
Right?
It seems that if you have an image...
that can give you pleasure...
then it must be able to give you pain.
Pain, yes.
There's no way out of that.
Absolutely.
Well, the image tends to be self-perpetuating...
like you were saying about the correlation.
Yes, but I think people hope...
that the image will give them pleasure.
Pleasure only.
Only pleasure.
But the very mechanism that makes pleasure possible...
makes pain possible.
Makes pain possible.
Because, you see, the pleasure comes...
if I say I think I am good...
and that I is also sensed to be real...
which makes that goodness real.
But then if somebody comes along and says...
you are no good, you are stupid and so on...
then that too is real.
And therefore very significant.
I mean, it makes it hurt. Right?
The image brings both pleasure and pain.
Yes.
Put it very, very simply.
Right.
I think people would hope for an image...
that would bring all the pleasure...
but it can't be done.
Well, people do hope.
There's no question about it.
People not only hope for the image...
but they invest all of their interest in their image.
They see themselves as...
they say I should not be this way...
because I am in fact the image.
So that they go both ways at the same time.
That's the most curious thing about the mind.
I am the image...
but when I discover that I am not the image...
then I should be that way...
because I really am that.
So it works both ways.
But the image...
you see I think that...
if you make the self-image...
and you get what's implied in there...
is to say everything depends on...
having this self-image right.
You see, in other words...
That's right. Everything...
The value of everything depends on...
this self-image being right.
So if somebody shows it's wrong...
therefore everything is no good.
Everything is wrong.
We are always giving new shape to the image.
That's right.
But I think that this image means everything.
So it gives a tremendous power.
The entire personality is directed...
to the achievement of this image.
In other words, everything else takes second place.
Are you aware of this?
Yes.
I'm aware of it.
What is the beginning of this?
Well...
Please, just to summarize first.
Every human being practically...
has an image about himself.
That's right.
Of which he is unconscious...
or not aware.
That's right.
And usually it's some sort of idealized...
Idealized or not idealized.
It's an image.
That's right.
It's an image, it's idealized...
and they must have it.
They have it.
I mean they must get all their actions...
toward mother.
They must have it.
In other words, to accomplish it.
Right.
I think one feels one's whole life is involved...
depends on the image.
Do you see that?
Yes.
That's right.
Depression is when I don't have it.
We'll come to that.
Then the next question...
how does it come into being?
Well, I think it comes into being...
when as children...
there is this hurt.
And there is the feeling...
that there is no other way...
in which this hurt can be...
assuaged or relieved.
It works in the family in some way.
You are my father...
and I understand through my watching you...
that if I am smart...
you will like me.
Right?
I learned that very quickly.
So I am going to make sure...
I get that love.
So I am going to go from here to there.
I am going to become that.
It's all very simple.
But I am asking the beginning of it.
The origin of making images...
about oneself.
Yes.
You see, if I had no image at all...
then I would never get into that, would I?
Yes, that's what I want to get at.
You see, why does...
Because I never made images.
Yes, if I never made any image at all...
then no matter what my father did...
that would have no effect.
I think that's a very important question.
I am saying maybe the child can't do it.
I am not sure.
He probably can.
Perhaps he can.
But I am saying at least under ordinary conditions...
he doesn't manage to do it.
You are suggesting that the child...
already has an image that has been hurt.
No, no, I don't know.
We are asking.
But suppose there were a child...
who made no images of himself.
Okay, let's assume he has no image.
Then he cannot get hurt.
He can't be hurt.
Well, now there you see...
I think you are in very hot water...
psychologically, because a child...
No, we said suppose.
Suppose.
Not the actual child that you know...
but rather suppose there were a child...
who didn't make an image of himself...
so he didn't depend on that image for everything.
You see, the child you talk about...
depended on the image that his father loves him.
That's right.
And therefore everything goes...
when his father doesn't love him.
Everything is gone.
And therefore he is hurt.
That's right.
But if he has no image...
that he must have his father love him...
then he will just watch his father.
The child who is watching his father...
but let's look at it a little more pragmatically.
Here is the child...
and he is actually hurt.
Well, wait.
He can't be hurt without the image.
What's going to get hurt?
Okay, there is no...
It's like putting a pin into the air.
No, now wait a second.
Now wait a minute.
I'm not going to let you
guys get away with this one.
Here you've got this child...
very vulnerable...
in the sense that he needs physiological support.
He has enormous tensions.
Sir, agreed to all that.
Such a child has an image.
No, no image.
He simply is not biologically being supported.
Right.
No.
Well, he may make an image of the fact...
that he is not biologically supported.
You see, you have to get the difference...
between the actual fact that happens biologically...
and what he thinks of it.
Now, you see, I've seen a child...
sometimes dropped suddenly...
and he really goes to pieces...
not because he was dropped very far...
but because that sense of...
No, insecurity.
...security from his mother was gone.
I mean, it seemed that everything had gone, right?
And he was totally disorganized and screaming...
though he dropped only about this far, you see.
But the point is he had an image...
of the kind of security he was going to get...
from his mother, right?
Well, that's the way the nervous system works.
Well, that's the question, is it?
I think we're discussing.
Is it necessary to work that way...
or is this the result of conditioning?
Yes. I would say yes.
Sir, this is an important question.
Oh, that's terribly important.
Because when you have been in America...
or this country...
children are running away from their parents.
Thousands are running away.
The parents seem to have no control over them.
They don't obey, they don't listen...
you follow? They are wild.
And the parents feel terribly hurt.
I saw on the TV what is happening in America.
And the woman was in tears, you follow?
She said, I am her mother...
he doesn't treat me as a mother.
He just orders me, give me a bottle of milk...
and the rest of it.
And he has run away half a dozen times.
And this is growing.
The separation between the parents...
and the children are growing...
all over the world.
They have no relationship between each other.
So, what is the cause of all this?
Apart from sociological, economic pressures...
and all that, which makes the mother go and work...
and leave the child alone...
you know, all that, take that for granted...
but much deeper than that.
Is it the parents have an image about themselves...
and the parents insist in
creating an image in the children?
I see what you are saying.
And the child refuses to have that image...
but he has his own image.
So the battle is on.
That's very much what I am saying...
when I say that initially the hurt of the child...
We haven't come to the hurt yet.
Well, but that's where...
I am trying to get at what is...
in that initial relationship.
What is the initial relationship between child...
I doubt if they have any relation.
That's what I am trying to point out.
That's right. I agree with you.
There is something wrong with the relationship.
They have a relationship...
but it's a wrong relationship.
Have their relationship.
They have a...
Look, young people get married...
or not married.
They have a child.
Right.
By mistake or intentionally they have a child.
The young people, they are children themselves.
They haven't understood the
universe, cosmos, order or chaos.
They just have this child.
That's right.
That's right. That's what happens.
And they play with it for a year or two...
and they say, for God's sake,
I am fed up with this child.
And then look elsewhere.
And the child feels left, lost.
That's right.
And he needs security.
Right.
From the beginning he needs security.
Which the parents cannot give...
or are incapable of giving.
Psychological security.
The sense of, you are my child...
I love you, I look after you...
I will see that throughout life you behave properly.
Care.
They haven't got that, that feeling.
Right.
They are bored with it after a couple of years.
That's right.
Right?
Is it that they have no relationship...
right from the beginning...
neither the husband nor the wife...
a boy or a girl...
it's only a sexual relationship?
Right.
The pleasure relationship...
which they...
in accepting that...
they won't accept the pleasure...
the pain principle involved in pleasure principle.
Right.
That's right.
They won't, and not only that...
they won't let the child go through that.
The child is going through that.
Yes, but they do things that...
they don't let the child have the pleasure...
that goes all the way...
nor do they let the child have the pain that...
So what I am trying to...
see is that there is actually...
no relationship at all...
except biological...
sexual, sensory relationship.
Yes, okay.
I am questioning.
I am not saying it is so.
I am questioning it.
I don't think it's so.
I think that they have a relationship...
but it's a wrong relationship...
that there are all kinds of...
There is no wrong relationship.
It is a relationship or no relationship.
Then we will have to say...
they have a relationship.
Now we will have to understand...
the relationship.
But I think that most parents...
have a relationship with their child.
When you say it's the image...
that's related, you say...
suppose the parent and child...
have images of each other...
and the relationship is governed...
by those images.
Now the question is whether...
that is actually a relationship or not...
or whether it's some sort of...
fantasy of a relationship.
A fanciful relationship.
Yes, you see...
Sir, put it...
you have children.
Forgive me if I come back to you.
You have children.
Have you any relationship with them?
No, in the real sense of that word.
Yes.
In the real sense, yes.
That means you have no image...
about yourself.
Right.
And you are not imposing...
an image on them.
That's right.
And the society is not imposing...
an image on them.
There are moments like that.
They are not good enough...
like a rotten egg.
This is an important point.
If it's moments, it's not so.
It's like saying a person who is hurt...
has moments when he is not hurt...
but is sitting there waiting to explode...
when something happens.
Happens, yes.
You see, so he can't go very far.
He is like somebody who is tied to a rope.
As soon as he reaches the limits of his life...
to that rope, he is stuck.
That's right.
So you could say I am related...
as long as certain things are all right.
But then beyond that point...
it sort of just blows up.
You see what I am driving at?
I see what you are driving at.
That mechanism is inside there...
buried so that it dominates you potentially.
In fact, what you just said is fact.
I mean, I'll verify that that's what happens.
In other words, there are the...
it seems that there are...
moments in which there are...
Well, it's like the man
who is tied to a rope...
and he says there are moments...
when I can move wherever I like...
but then I can't really...
because if I keep on moving...
I am bound to come to the end.
Well, that does seem to be what happens.
In fact, there is a reverberation...
in which there is a yank back.
Either I come to the end of the cord...
or something yanks the cord.
But the person who is on the cord...
is really not free, ever.
Well, that's true.
I mean, I think that's true.
That's true.
And see, in the same sense...
the person who has the image...
is not really related ever, you see.
That's just the whole point.
You can play with it.
You can play with the verbal...
but actually you have no relationship.
You have no relationship...
as long as it's the image.
As long as you have an image about yourself...
you have no relationship.
That's right.
With another.
This is a tremendous revelation.
You follow?
It's not just an intellectual statement.
Let me share with you something.
I resent this...
I see that.
You see that.
I mean, I get rather angry with you.
I see it.
You know, I mean, there's a real...
and we've seen this in other places...
Well, it always happens with analysis, doesn't it?
Well, it always happens with analysis...
but I mean, I was thinking we had psychotherapy...
the meeting with the psychotherapist...
this came up.
There's a tremendous resentment to say that...
I mean, because I have the memory of times...
when I do have what I think is a relationship...
yet I must be honest with you...
and say that after such relationship...
there inevitably seems to be this yank back.
The yanking of the cord, yes.
The yank back.
So that I must...
I mean...
There is that.
I mean, there's no question that the image...
there is a place where you say...
you'll have a relationship with somebody...
but you will go just so far.
Yes.
Of course.
And that's where the image comes in.
That's right.
But then really the image controls it all the time...
because you say the image is the dominant factor.
If you're once past that point...
no matter what happens...
the image takes over.
That's right.
It's like something...
It's very much like that stuff of René Tom's...
in other words...
it goes right down.
So the image gets hurt.
And the child...
do you impose an image on the child?
Because you are bound to...
because you have an image.
You're trying to.
You have to.
Well, no, you're working at it...
and the child picks it up...
or he doesn't pick it up.
No, no.
Because you have an image about yourself...
you're bound to create an image in the child.
That's right.
That's it.
You follow?
You've discovered.
Yes.
And society is doing this to all of us.
So you say the child is...
you know, is picking up an image...
just naturally, as it were...
quietly, and then suddenly it gets hurt, right?
Hurt, that's right.
So the hurt has been prepared and preceded...
by this steady process of building an image, right?
That's right.
Well, you know, there is evidence...
that shows, for instance, we treat boys...
different than we treat girls.
Look at it.
Don't verbalize it too quickly.
You see, if this steady process...
of building an image didn't occur...
then there would be no basis...
no structure to get hurt.
You see, that's the...
Mm-hm.
In other words, the pain is...
due entirely to some psychological factor...
some thought which is attributed to me...
you see, in saying, I am suffering this pain.
Mm-hm.
Whereas I was previously enjoying the pleasure...
of saying, my father loves me...
I'm doing what he wants, right?
And now comes the pain...
I'm not doing what he wants...
and he doesn't love me.
But what about the initial hurts?
I mean, the child...
No, if you want...
No, I think we've got it beyond that point.
Beyond that point.
I don't think we've touched on the fact...
of the biological situation...
of the child...
the child feeling...
Neglected.
Well, but that's still...
what do you mean?
If the child is neglected...
I mean, I think that
he must pick up an image...
in that very process.
Of course.
If you admit...
once you admit...
see the reality...
that as long as the parents have...
an image about themselves...
they are bound to give that image to the child.
An image.
It's the image which makes the parent neglect the child.
Yeah, well, you're right there.
It is right.
There's no question...
as long as the parent is an image maker...
and has an image...
then he has nothing...
he can't see the child.
And he can't see the child.
And therefore gives an image to the child.
Right.
He'll condition the child...
to be into something.
Yes.
And at first perhaps through pleasure...
then he'll get hurt.
But if he begins by neglecting him...
see, I think the process of neglect...
is also the result of an image...
and he must communicate an image to the child...
as he neglects the child.
Which is neglect.
Yes, that neglect is the image...
he is communicating.
That's right.
And also the parents are bound to neglect...
if they have an image about themselves.
That's right.
It must because...
Inevitably.
That's right.
Because they are fragmenting...
rather than seeing the whole.
Yes, the child will get the image...
that he doesn't matter to his parents...
you know...
except in that fragment.
Yes, in the fragment they like and so on.
That's right.
So if you are this way...
I'm with you.
If you are not that way...
But you see...
society is doing this to every human being.
Right?
Church is doing it.
Churches, religions, politics...
everything, culture...
around us is creating this image.
That's right.
And that image gets hurt...
and all the rest of it.
Now, next question is...
is one aware of all this?
Which is part of our consciousness.
Right, right.
The content of consciousness...
makes up consciousness.
Right?
That's clear.
Right.
What...
So, one of the contents...
is the image making.
Or maybe the major machinery...
that is operating.
The major dynamo...
the major movement.
Being hurt...
whichever human being is...
can that hurt be healed...
and never be hurt again?
That is, can a human mind...
which has created...
which has accepted the image...
which creates the image...
put away the image completely...
and never be hurt?
Right.
And therefore...
in consciousness...
a great part of it is...
is empty...
it has no content.
I wonder...
Mm-hmm.
Kenneth...
what is the difference...
between the two?
What is the difference...
I really don't know...
the answer to that.
Why?
I know the answer...
only that I...
I believe you could...
Who is the image maker?
What is the machinery...
or the process...
that is making image...
making images?
I may get rid of one image...
and take on another.
I am a Catholic...
I am a Protestant...
I am a Hindu...
I am a Zen monk...
I am this...
I am that...
You follow?
They are all images.
Right.
Who is the image maker?
You see, after all...
if there is an image...
of that kind...
how can you have love?
In all this?
We don't have an abundance of it.
We don't have it!
That's right.
We've got a lot of images.
That's why I say...
I don't know.
I know about image making.
It is terrible, sir...
to have this.
You follow?
Right.
I know about image making...
and I see it...
now even as you are talking about it...
I can see it there...
and the feeling is one of...
it's like a map.
You know where you are at.
Because if I don't make this image...
I'll make another.
Of course.
If you don't make this one...
you'll make another.
We are saying...
is it possible...
to stop the machinery...
that is producing the images?
Yes.
And what is the machinery?
Is it wanting to be somebody?
Yes.
It's wanting to be somebody.
It's wanting to know where...
wanting to have...
to reduce...
well, somehow or other...
it seems to be wanting...
to handle the feeling...
that if I don't have it...
I don't know where I'm at.
Being at a loss?
Yes.
See how clever...
see being at a loss...
you follow?
The feeling that you are at a loss...
not to rely on anything...
not to have any support...
breeds more disorder.
You follow?
Right.
Well, that's one of the images...
was communicated to it as a child...
to say that if you don't have...
an image of yourself...
you don't know what to do at all.
That is...
You don't know what your parents...
are going to do...
if you start acting without an image.
I mean, you may do something...
and they will just simply be horrified.
That's right.
The image is the product of thought.
Right?
It's organized.
Yes, a product of thought.
It may go through various forms of...
pressures and all the rest of it...
a great deal of conveyor belts...
and at the end...
you see an image.
Right.
No question.
I agree with you there.
It's definitely the product of thought...
and that thought seems to be like...
the immediate action...
in knowing where you're at...
or in trying to know where you're at.
It's like there's a space.
So can the machinery stop?
Can thought, which produces these images...
which destroys all relationship...
and therefore no love...
not verbally, actually no love...
don't say, yes, I love my...
when a man who has got an image about himself...
and says, I love my husband or wife...
or my children...
is just sentiment, romanticism...
fanciful, emotionalism.
Right.
So, as it is now...
there is no love in the world.
Right.
There is no sense of real caring for somebody.
That's true.
People don't, right?
The more affluent...
the worse it becomes.
Right.
Not that the poor have this...
I don't mean...
poor people haven't got this either.
They're after filling their stomachs...
and clothes...
and work, work, work, work.
But still they've got lots of images.
Of course.
I said both the rich and the poor...
have these images.
Including Bezhnev and Sakharov...
or whoever it is.
And these are the people...
who are correcting the world.
Right?
Who say, well, this...
You follow?
They are the ordering of the universe...
of the...
So, I ask myself...
can this image-making stop?
Stop.
Not occasionally.
Stop it.
Yes.
Because then I don't know...
what love means.
I don't know how to care for somebody.
And I think that is what is...
happening in the world.
Because children are really lost souls...
lost human beings.
I've met so many...
hundreds of them now...
all over the world.
They are really lost generations.
You understand?
As the older people are lost...
lost generations, they are...
So, what is a human being...
to do?
What is his right action...
in relationship?
Can there be right action...
in relationship...
as long as you have an image?
No, sir.
This is a tremendous thing.
You follow?
That's why I was wondering...
you see, it seemed to me...
you made a jump there...
that you said...
all we know...
all we know somehow or other...
is images...
and image-making...
and thought.
That's all we know.
But we never said...
can it stop?
We've never said...
That's right.
We never said...
for God's sake...
if it doesn't stop...
we are going to destroy each other.
You see, you could say that now...
the notion that it might stop...
is something more that we know...
that we didn't know before.
It becomes another piece of knowledge.
Yes, but...
I was trying to say that...
when you say all we know...
it's the same thing as before.
I mean, I feel that...
that block comes in.
Oh, you're back to that.
You see, in other words...
it's not much use to say...
all we know.
Because he said...
can it stop?
Can it stop?
If you say that's all we know...
then it could never stop.
He's objecting to your use of all.
I think that's what makes it...
I'm grateful for you.
That's one of the factors...
blocking it.
Yes.
Well, if we come down to it...
I mean, what do we do with that question...
can it stop?
I mean, there we are.
We've got this question.
Can it stop?
I put that question to you.
Do you listen to it?
I listen, right.
Do you listen?
And it stops for a while.
No, no, no.
I'm not interested in it.
Do you listen to a statement?
Can it stop?
We now examine, analyse or examine...
this whole process of image making...
the result of it...
the misery, the confusion...
the appalling things that are going on.
The Arab has his image...
the Jew, the Hindu, the Muslim...
the Christian, the non-Christian...
you follow?
Right.
It's this tremendous division of images...
symbols, all the rest of it.
If that doesn't stop...
you're going to have such a chaotic world.
You follow?
I see this, not as an abstraction...
as an actuality, as the thought...
as the thought itself.
Right.
And I feel, as a human being...
what am I to do?
Because I personally have no image about it.
I really mean I have no image about myself...
a conclusion, a concept, an ideal...
all these are images.
I have none.
And I say to myself...
I'm a man, I don't.
And everybody around me is building images.
And so destroying this lovely earth...
where we are meant to live happily...
you know, in human relationship...
and look at the heavens and be happy about it.
So what is the right of the human being...
what is the right action...
for a man who has an image?
Or there is no right action...
Let me turn it back.
What happens with you when I say to you...
can it stop?
I say, of course.
It's very simple to me.
Of course it can stop.
You don't ask me the next question...
how do you do it?
How does it come about?
No, I want to just listen for a minute...
to when you say, yes, of course.
Okay, now, how do you think it can?
Five minutes.
Well, only five minutes.
Okay, well, let's just touch...
how can it stop?
I have no...
let me put it to you straight.
Let's see if I can get it straight.
I have absolutely no evidence that it can.
No experience that it can, except flashes.
I don't want evidence.
You don't want any evidence.
I don't want somebody's explanation.
Or experience.
Because they are based on images.
Right.
Future image or past image...
or living image.
Okay.
So I say, can it stop?
Yes.
Okay.
I say it can.
Definitely.
It's not just a verbal statement to amuse you.
To me this is tremendously important.
Well, I think we agree that it's tremendously important.
But how?
And it...
not how.
Then you enter into the
question of systems, mechanical process.
Which is part of our image making.
If I tell you how, then you
tell me the system, the method, the practice.
I'll do it every day
and I'll get the new image.
Yes.
Now, I see the fact
that's going on in the world.
I got it.
I'm with you, yes.
Fact.
Not my reactions to it.
Not my romantic, fanciful theories what it should not be.
It is a fact that
as long as there are images...
there's no going to be peace in
the world, no love in the world.
Whether the Christ image or the
Buddha image or the Muslim image...
you follow?
There won't be peace in the world.
Right?
I see it as a fact.
Right.
Right?
I remain with that fact.
That's all.
Finished.
As this morning we said,
if one remains with the fact...
there is a transformation.
There is a transformation.
Which is not to let the...
not...
thought begins to interfere with the fact.
Well, the same as this morning to say...
more images come in as a matter of fact.
More images come in.
So our consciousness is filled with these images.
Yes, that's true.
I'm a Hindu, Brahmin, I am my tradition...
I am better than anybody else.
I am the chosen of people.
I am the Aryan.
You follow?
I am the only Englishman.
All that is crowding my consciousness.
Well, see, when you say...
to remain with the fact...
one of the images that may come in is...
that it's impossible or that it can never be done.
Never, yes.
That's another image.
See, in other words...
if the mind could stay with that fact...
with no comment whatsoever...
That's right.
Well, the thing that comes through to me...
when you say that...
is that when you say remain with the fact...
you are really calling for...
an action right there.
To really remain with it is that the action...
of perception is there.
Sir, you don't...
why do you make it so much...
It is around you.
You are involved in it.
But that's different from remaining with it.
Remain with that.
To really see it.
Yes, that's all.
That's...
You know how that feels?
It feels like something...
carries forward.
Because we are always running away.
So our consciousness, sir...
is this image.
Conclusions, ideas...
Always running away.
Filling, filling.
And that's the essence of the image.
If I have no...
if there is no...
image making...
then what is consciousness?
That's quite a difference.
Do you think we could discuss that next time?
Tomorrow, we'll see.